When I was in elementary school, I had friends just like everyone else.
上小学时 我跟其他人一样有很多小伙伴
GROUNDS PUBLIC POOL
（运动场 公共泳池）
During summer break, we'd play at the public pool every day until sunset.
每逢暑假 我们天天都会去公共泳池 一直玩到太阳下山
Thinking back on it, my life peaked back then.
回想起来 那真是我生命中的巅峰
When I got to middle school,
等到上了中学
everyone began to notice I was naturally an introvert.
大家开始注意到我其实生性内向
Before I knew it, I was on the outside looking in.
不知不觉间 我就被排挤在外了
During my three years in high school, I didn't talk to anyone
高中的那三年 我没跟任何人说话
and spent my time reading while listening to Rakugo stories.
总是一边听着落语一边看书
In college, I tried to change myself.
上大学时 我尝试过改变自己
I did an overseas internship.
我去过海外实习
I was a student volunteer.
当过学生志愿者
And I even took a personal development seminar.
甚至还参加了个人成长研讨会
But to everyone else, I was just an empty, visionless, self-conscious idiot.
但所有人都觉得我就是个内心空虚 毫无远见、自我意识过强的傻子
To be fair, I didn't know
结果 我也不知道
-what I wanted to do with myself. -They'll upsize beef bowls for free!
-我对自己有什么规划 -那里的肥牛饭能免费升级成大碗！
What? For real?
什么？真的假的？
We have to go! I could eat three bowls!
我们去吧！我能吃三碗！
You're definitely going to barf them up during practice.
你肯定会在训练的时候吐出来的
It's fine! I'll be fine this time!
没事的！这次绝对没问题！
Didn't you say something like that before?
你上回好像也是这么说的吧？
-That was five servings of pasta. -He should have been like me.
-那回我可是吃了五份意面呀 -他就该像我一样
-Empty, visionless, lacking ambition. -No way. That would be six bowls!
-内心空虚、毫无远见、胸无大志 -哪有 明明是六碗！
-But he… -Nope, I can do it today!
-可他… -我今天绝对没问题
…cruised through life without a care in the world.
却成天无忧无虑的 活得这么轻松
He's always enjoying himself!
总是在享受生活！
And I just couldn't help but despise him.
我真是没办法不讨厌这家伙
What's the matter?
怎么了？
Come on out already.
快出来呀
Your dad is weeping over what a good son he has!
有你这么不孝的儿子 你爸都哭了！
I have to save Dad!
我必须救爸爸
But that means I need to become a zombie?
但要救爸爸 我就得变成僵尸？
What am I supposed to do?
我该怎么办？
Don't you dare open that door, Akira.
无论如何都不准开门 阿辉
If you put your mom in danger and make me watch my own kid die,
你要敢让你妈妈陷入危险 让我亲眼看着自己的孩子死掉
we're no longer family.
我就不认你这个儿子
But if I don't do anything, you're going to…
但如果我什么都不做的话 你会…
Don't worry about me, Akira.
别担心我 阿辉
Either way, I don't have long left.
不管你开不开门 我都活不长了
What?
什么？
Your father has got one of those bad growths on his body.
你爸爸身体里长了一些不好的东西
With everything that's happening, there are no doctors or medicine…
而如今这缺医少药的环境
There's no way to treat it.
没办法给他医治
Sooner or later, it'll be too late for him.
他迟早会没救的
But you don't know that for sure.
但眼下一切都还没有定数
If we search for a doctor, we might find one right away.
如果我们去找医生 也许马上就能找到呢？
And a vaccine to deal with the zombies could be developed tomorrow!
而且说不定 僵尸疫苗明天就能研发出来呢？
At this rate, I'll never have a chance to show you my gratitude.
可是照这样下去 我就再也没有机会向你尽孝了
Akira,
阿辉
help humanity.
去帮助其他人吧
Do what you can for the world.
尽你所能 为世界出一份力
Don't lie for your own sake.
不要为了一己私利而撒谎
Show others empathy.
也要理解别人的痛苦
You can give back to us, even if we're gone.
即使我们不在了 你依然可以回报我们
To see you living strong from up in heaven…
只要能在天上看着你坚强地生活
There's nothing that would make me prouder.
我就会感到无比的自豪
Haven't you ever wanted to see Earth from the far reaches of space?
难道你没有渴想过 到太空中遥望地球吗？
Take care of your mom.
照顾好你妈妈
Thanks for worrying about me.
谢谢你的关心
But aren't you exhausted from your long journey?
但你大老远赶回来 不觉得累吗？
I was a makeup artist for films.
我是电影剧组的化妆师
You'd never expect to be attacked by real zombies.
谁能想到会遭遇真正的僵尸袭击呢？
It doesn't seem like he's coming out.
他似乎是不打算出来了
I guess some half-dead old guy isn't much of a hostage.
果然一个半死不活的老头当不成人质
You damned fool!
你这傻孩子！
I did it!
我成功了
Finally!
终于！
I turned the person I hate the most into a zombie!
我终于让我最讨厌的人变成了僵尸！
Look at you!
瞧瞧你这副鬼样子！
Now I'll never have to see that dumbass smile of yours again!
现在我再也不用看你傻笑了！
The fun times are over for you, and you can't do what you want anymore!
你的快乐时光结束了 你再也不能做自己想做的事了！
I win!
我赢了！
100 THINGS WE WANT TO DO BEFORE BECOMING ZOMBIES
（变成僵尸前想做的100件事）
What?
什么？
What is this?
这是怎么回事？
What the hell is going on?
这什么情况啊？
I'm sorry.
对不起
This is a risky plan, but I'd like to ask everyone for their help.
我想到了一个很冒险的计划 但还是想请大家帮忙
We'll create dark recesses for your eyes, hollow out your cheeks, make some bruises…
画上黑眼圈 在面颊上画出 凹陷的效果 再来点淤青
For the blood, we'll make it sticky by adding laundry detergent.
至于血嘛 我们就加入一些洗衣液来让它变粘稠
For discolored teeth, we'll use brown alcohol based ink.
至于牙齿的污垢 就用棕色的酒精颜料
Finally, we'll give you white contacts!
最后 给你戴上白色的隐形眼镜
I totally look like a zombie!
不管怎么看 我都是僵尸啦！
22. ATTEMPT COSPLAY
（22 尝试变装秀）
It's all up to you, Akira!
接下来就看你的了 阿辉
I got this!
包在我身上！
Are you all right, Dad?
你没事吧 爸爸？
Yeah. I can still move.
嗯 我还能动
Damn it!
可恶
Higurashi, what did you want to do, anyway?
日暮 你到底想怎么样呀？
The same thing as you!
和你一样！
To do whatever I wanted! Anything I wanted!
随心所欲！做我想做的事！
Is it so wrong for me to have some fun for once?
我就想开心地玩一次 难道有错吗？
If this is really what you wanted to do…
如果这真是你想要的…
then why didn't you look like you were having any fun?
那你为什么看起来一点也不开心？
Of course I'm having fun!
我当然开心了！
This is exactly what I…
这就是我…
wanted to do?
想做的事？
Higurashi. Higurashi!
日暮！
What is it?
搞什么啊？
What the hell have you done?
你做了什么？
Damn it!
可恶！
Let's go, Akira.
我们走吧 阿辉
The zombies are already coming this way.
僵尸已经朝这边过来了
What's on your real list?
你真正的清单是什么？
What did you want to write down on your real bucket list, Higurashi?
你真正想在愿望清单上 写下的是什么 日暮？
The thing I really wanted to do…
我真正想做的事…
Whoa! Watch out for the water!
哇！小心别溺水啦！
That was a huge dive.
你在水下面待了好久
I lost.
我输了
All right!
来喽！
You went overboard, Higurashi!
你太夸张了啦 日暮！
All I wanted to do…
我真正想做的事
was have fun at the public pool with my friends.
就是在公共泳池跟朋友们一起玩
If that's all, then, you were a fool, Higurashi.
要只是这样的话 那你真是个大笨蛋 日暮
Nope, I can do it today! It's because I didn't have breakfast yet!
今天绝对没问题！ 因为我还没吃早饭呢！
You're in the same Gen-Ed program as me, aren't you?
你是我一般教养课程的同学 对吧？
If you're hungry, want to come with us?
饿了的话 要不要跟我们一起去吃？
What's with that guy? He left without saying anything.
那家伙怎么回事啊？ 一句话不说就走了
Let's get going already. They might run out!
我们快去吧 免得肥牛饭卖光啦
You should have just told us…
你那个时候如果把心愿
what you wanted back then.
直接告诉我们就好了
If the time comes when I really become a zombie,
假如有一天我真的变成了僵尸
let's go to the pool together, okay?
我们就一起去泳池玩吧 好吗？
25. GIVE FREE HUGS
（25 免费送上拥抱）
Let's go.
我们走吧
GROUNDS PUBLIC POOL
（运动场 公共泳池）
Hey!
喂！
Akiko and everyone! Are you all right?
阿辉还有大家！你们都还好吧？
Is that you, Kencho?
阿宪 是你吗？
Akira! Why are you a zombie?
阿辉！你怎么成僵尸了？
Something stinks!
什么东西这么臭？
Everyone! You're all right!
你们都没事 太好了！
This is everyone from the village.
村民们都在这儿了
This is bad.
情况不妙
We need to get out of here now!
我们得赶紧离开这儿！
But how can we get past this fence?
但我们要怎么穿过电网呀？
Everyone! Out of the way please!
大家请让开！
Bea?
贝雅？
I can't seem to get down, so I must crash this into the electrical fence!
我好像下不来了 所以只好踩着这东西撞开电网啦！
Everyone! Get away from the fence and open up a path!
大家请远离电网 让出一条道来！
All healthy bodies, give the old folks a hand!
身体强健的朋友 请帮忙搀扶一下老人！
Leave it to us!
交给我们吧！
Here I go!
我来啦！
Now!
就是现在！
Everyone, run!
大家快跑！
Just a little further until the suspension bridge!
再往前一点就是吊桥了！
No way.
怎么会这样？
The suspension bridge…
吊桥…
It was our only way out.
这是我们唯一的出路呀
Damn it!
可恶！
Isn't there anything we can do?
没有其他办法了吗？
Hey, guys!
嘿 各位！
Take this!
接住喽！
You're…
你是…
Mr. Kumano!
熊野先生！
I came to see what the zombies were up in arms about
我想来看看僵尸怎么忽然那么亢奋
only to see your bridge was out!
结果发现你们的吊桥断了
I built you a brand new one in a jiffy!
我就火速给你们造了个新的！
I told you I'd help you out if you ran into any trouble!
我就说你们要是遇到了麻烦 我一定会帮忙的吧？
They're already here!
僵尸追过来了！
We'll hold up the bridge!
我们来扶住吊桥！
Get across now!
大家快过去！
Hurry!
快！
Everyone got across!
大家快过桥！
You ready for this, Kencho?
你准备好了吗 阿宪？
You bet, Akira!
那必须的 阿辉
This is super scary!
超可怕！
-Ouch!
-好痛！
He just wanted friends?
他想要的只是朋友而已？
If that's really all Higurashi wanted, then he's a god damned fool.
如果那真的是日暮唯一的心愿 那他真是个大傻瓜
Yeah.
是啊
But when I was working for that exploitative company,
但我在为黑心企业打工的时候
I also lost sight of myself.
也同样迷失了自我
Every day was so painful and I didn't know what I was living for.
每天都活得很痛苦 不知道活着有什么意义
If I had wanted to make my own twisted list like that black notebook,
如果我当时想写下那样扭曲的清单 就像那本黑色笔记本
I could have.
不仅是我
Anyone could've become like Higurashi.
任何人都有可能变成日暮
So despite everything, I can't hate him.
所以尽管发生了这些事 我还是没办法恨他
There we go.
好了
Good job, Akira.
好样的 阿辉
Without you, your mom and everyone in the village wouldn't be here.
多亏有你在 你妈妈和全村的人才能幸免于难
I'm proud of you, son!
我真为你骄傲 儿子！
So, does this mean I was able to repay you just a little?
那我是不是 有稍微回报了你们一点呀？
38. GIVE BACK TO MY PARENTS
（38 回报父母）
Now! Seal it off!
好了 封堵隧道！
Are those all the zombies?
那些是所有僵尸了吗？
We searched every inch of the village!
我们把村里的每个角落都搜遍了
There's no mistaking!
绝对没有遗漏！
You're planning on restarting here in the village?
你们想从这里开始重建村庄？
Well, we only have one hometown.
这毕竟是我们唯一的家乡呀
Now that Mr. Kumano has moved here and is leading the rebuilding,
而且熊野先生也搬了过来 领导重建工事
everyone is peppier than ever.
大家都前所未有地充满干劲呢
It seems like they got a second shot at life.
就好像重获新生了一样
I expect it won't be long before the village is back to the way it was before.
希望用不了多久 村子就能恢复昔日的风采
It's all thanks to you.
这都是多亏了你呀
You were our village doctor, remember?
你是我们村里的医生 记得吗？
Not really! I'm not even a doctor!
没有啦！我甚至都不是真正的医生
You cured us old whiners when we were ready to give in.
是你在我们想要放弃时 挽救了我们这群爱发牢骚的老骨头
I can't thank you enough.
我怎么谢你都不够呀
-Hold this. -Okay.
-扶着这个 -好的
Steadier! Otherwise, we won't finish before dinner!
扶稳一点！ 不然我们没法赶在晚饭前完工了！
Okay!
好！
Angie, you're like an entirely different person.
小杏 你好像完全变了个人似的
Crying won't repair this fence!
靠眼泪可修不好电网呀
And besides, I don't want to keep crying over zombies.
再说了 我不想再因为僵尸哭泣了
I was able to move forward because a funny guy got me to smile.
我之所以能向前看 多亏了一个有趣的家伙逗我笑呀
Thank you, Mr. Stand-Up Comic!
谢谢你 谐星先生！
34. BECOME A STAND-UP COMIC
（34 成为谐星）
He's sleeping well.
他睡得挺香的
He wore himself ragged up until now…
他脑子里那根弦 一直紧绷着 直到现在
Everyday he'd ask me,
他每天都会问我
"Have we heard from Akira yet?" "Is Akira doing all right?"
“有阿辉的消息吗？阿辉还好吗？”
Well, in a world full of zombies, even a curmudgeon like Dad would…
在这个僵尸横行的世界 连爸爸这样暴脾气的人也会…
No, not that!
不 不是的！
He started asking the day after you left for Tokyo.
打从你去东京的第二天起 他就开始这么问了
If…
假如…
I'm not saying that it will, but…
假如有那么一天…
If anything happens to you, Dad, I promise that I'll always
假如爸爸你真的有什么不测 我保证 我一定会
keep Mom and the village safe!
守护妈妈和这个村子！
I'll do it for you, Dad!
我会为你守护好他们的 爸爸！
By the way, what does Dad have?
对了 爸爸得了什么病？
Hemorrhoids?
痔疮？
-That's it? Hemorrhoids? -That's right!
-是那个痔疮？ -没错！
Hemorrhoids?
痔疮？
He hates hospitals, so he didn't get them treated.
他讨厌去医院 所以没有及时治疗
So now, the bleeding is really bad.
发展到现在 出血已经很严重了
The pain is so terrible that he can't stand.
他甚至会疼得站不起来
It's awful.
太严重了
So then why is he wheezing?
那他为什么呼吸这么粗重？
Lately, it's been considerably hot in the countryside, even at night.
最近乡下格外炎热 就连晚上也一样
It makes it difficult for old-timers to sleep.
所以上了年纪的人很难睡好觉
But we can't ignore hemorrhoids!
但痔疮的问题绝对不容忽视！
If we leave them alone, they could lead to a life-threatening infection!
一直置之不理的话 它们有可能引发致命的感染！
I see. It's just hemorrhoids.
原来如此 只是痔疮而已
Find your dream, Akira.
你得找到自己的梦想呀 阿辉
Biggest one you can.
找个更大的梦想
A man without a dream is nothing more than a jellyfish.
没有梦想的男人跟咸鱼没什么分别
If that's the case, I think it's time for me to leave the village.
这样的话 我想我是时候离开村庄了
What about the village?
你走了村子怎么办？
Akira, what do you wish to do outside of the village?
阿辉 你想离开村子去做什么呢？
If the zombies are caused by a virus like Shizuka says,
如果真的像闲说的那样 这一切是由僵尸病毒导致的
I'll travel the country and look for a way to stop the infection.
那我要走遍全国 寻找阻止感染的办法
Then I'll convince Dad to get surgery for his hemorrhoids!
然后我会说服爸爸 让他做手术切除痔疮
"Help humanity." "Do what you can for the world."
“去帮助其他人吧 尽你所能 为世界出一份力”
Those were Dad's last wishes after all!
这毕竟是爸爸的遗愿呀！
-He's still alive though.
-可他还没死呢
Saving the world.
拯救世界
That's wild.
好狂妄呀
It's a big dream.
真是个宏大的梦想
I like it!
我喜欢！
40. MAKE DAD GET SURGERY
（40 让爸爸做痔疮手术）
What about all of you?
你们呢？
Is there anything you want to add?
还有什么想要补充的吗？
In that case, I'm adding one.
这样的话 我来添上一条
I'm sure there are lots of people across Japan who are crying like Angie!
在日本肯定还有很多 像小杏一样悲伤哭泣的人吧
This time, I want to fulfill my childhood dream!
这一次 我要实现儿时的梦想
42. BECOME A DOCTOR
（42 当医生）
So far, I've only toured the zombie infested parts of Nippon.
目前为止 我只游览过被僵尸占领的日本
43. RESTORE NIPPON'S NATURAL BEAUTY
（43 找回日本的美丽风景）
Very nice!
很好！
Let's keep it up and write all the things we'd like to do across Japan!
大家继续 我们来一起写下 所有想在日本做的事吧！
I want to party on a cruise ship!
我想在邮轮上开派对
I want to swim with dolphins!
我想和海豚一起游泳
I want to live in a castle!
我想住在一座城堡里
-How about a waterfall meditation? -I want to ride an ostrich!
-在瀑布下冥想怎么样？ -我想骑鸵鸟！
I've always wanted to eat Yobuko squid served live!
我一直想尝尝呼子町的活鱿鱼！
I want to experience hatsumōde at Ise Shrine.
我想去伊势神宫做新年参拜
-Me too! -Nice one!
-我也想！ -这个好！
We can do that!
我们一起去吧！
Got enough water?
水带够了吗？
Take some vegetables too!
也带上点蔬菜
It's going to get colder from here on.
从这里往后会越来越冷
Take whatever you need.
需要什么就尽管拿哦
Thank you so much!
太谢谢您啦
Akemi!
明美！
I'll always be waiting for you to come back, you hear?
我会一直等你回来的 知道吗？
Old Man Hiko, I'm not Akemi.
阿彦老头子 我不是明美
I'm Shizuka.
我是闲
It's going to get lonely, isn't it?
往后的日子会很孤单吧？
I think it's okay to cry in front of him since you're saying goodbye.
在这个分别的时刻 你在他面前哭一哭也是没关系的
Mr. Kencho!
阿宪哥哥！
When you come back, show me how you slurp udon with your butt!
等你回来了 要表演用屁股吃乌冬面给我看哦！
Enough already!
已经够多啦！
We don't need this much simmered seaweed!
我们吃不了这么多佃煮海带啦！
It's fine. Just take it.
没事的 拿着吧
It'll keep!
它能存放很久的
I don't like the idea of you going hungry somewhere.
我可不想你们在哪里饿肚子
Mom.
妈妈
Akira!
阿辉！
Leave your mother to me!
你妈妈就放心交给我照顾吧
Okay, everyone!
好了 大家
We're just going to go
我们要出发了
and save the world!
去拯救世界！
6. TRAVEL AROUND THE COUNTRY
（六 周游全国）
So, what's the plan, Akira?
你是怎么打算的 阿辉？
Stopping a virus means we'll need a vaccine, right?
要阻止病毒 就意味着我们需要疫苗 对吧？
Are we heading to an infectious disease research lab? A U.S. military base?
我们要去哪个传染病研究所吗？ 或者某个美国军事基地？
-We'll go north! -North?
-我们往北走！ -往北？
Because all good travelers venture north!
因为优秀的旅行家 都会往北展开冒险！
Isn't it exciting?
好激动呀 对吧？
Is it just me, or does it seem like we're just sightseeing?
是只有我这么觉得吗？ 感觉我们就是在观光而已
Are we really searching for a solution?
我们真的有在找解决办法吗？
I think it's all good!
我觉得还好啦！
Hey, it's coming into view!
嘿 看那边！
The Seikan Tunnel!
是青函隧道！
All right! Next up is Hokkaido!
好嘞！下一站 北海道！
Sounds good to me!
好主意！